Finding Aid for Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society. University of Michigan Chapter records, 1903-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society. University of Michigan Chapter records 1903-2001
Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society. University of Michigan Chapter.
87213 Bimu F41 2
University of Michigan Chapter of scientific research society. By-laws and membership rolls, minutes, secretary's files, treasurer's records, and programs of annual banquets.
4.3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by the chapter (Donor No. 5930 ) beginning in 1986. Additions have been received.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Sigma Xi, The Scientific Research Society, was founded in 1886 to encourage original investigations in science, pure and applied. A chapter of the organization was chartered at the University of Michigan in May 1903 by 35 faculty and graduates of the University. From the beginning, the Michigan chapter sought to integrate women by voting, reconsidering and reaffirming at the March 24, 1904, business meeting to admit women. Of the 29 students and five faculty members elected at that meeting, six were women.
Until 1913 membership was conducted by vote of the entire chapter and was afterward conducted by council alone. For the first decade, undergraduates were admitted based on scholarship, while graduates and faculty were admitted based on research. In 1914, the Michigan chapter went on record as favoring a new classification for admittance, which included an "associate membership" for those showing promise. Sigma Xi also figured in the movement to establish a grading system at the University in the early twentieth-century.
The records of the University of Michigan chapter of Sigma Xi date from 1903 to 2001. Noteworthy items include the early volumes of minutes, by-laws and membership records, and the records regarding the Centennial Celebration at which Stephen Jay Gould and Walter Sullivan spoke. Collection also contains videotapes, audio tapes, and the transcript from the society's 2001 forum.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Honorary societies.; Sigma Xi, the Scientific Research Society. University of Michigan Chapter.
- Organizational records
  - Administration 1961-1987
    - Activities
      - Grants 1980-1987 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
      - Lectures 1961-1986 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
      - Special Projects 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Annual Reports 1983-1987 (Box 1)
    - Council Meeting Agendas and Minutes
      - 1965-1967 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
      - 1979-1984 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
      - 1984-1988 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Financial 1961-1987 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Membership
      - Membership lists by type of membership (Box 1)
      - Nomination materials 1962-1987 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Officer Responsibilities (Box 1)
    - President's Reports 1985-1986, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Annual Banquet Programs
    - 1914-1948 (Box 1)
    - 1949-1975 (Box 1)
  - By-Laws and Membership Rolls
    - 1903-1959, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1960-1984 (some gaps), 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - Centennial Celebration
    - Financial Reports 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Planning Committee 1986 (Box 1)
    - Publicity 1986 (Box 1)
  - Certificates of Recognition
    - 1992 (Box 1)
    - 1993 (Box 1)
    - 1994 (Box 1)
  - History and Background
    - Description of Chapter History (Box 1)
    - Standards and By-Laws 1961 (Box 1)
  - Minute books
    - 1903-1930 (Box 1)
    - 1931-1943 (Box 1)
    - 1943-1953 (Box 1)
  - Officer List
    - 1903-1941 (Box 1)
    - 1944-1988 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Secretary's File
    - 1965-1985, 16 folders (Box 2)
  - Treasurer's Records
    - 1921-1937, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1937-1939, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Membership
    - Undated
      - Administrative (Box 2)
    - 1974-1982 (scattered)
      - Administrative (Box 2)
    - 1985
      - Administrative (Box 2)
      - Nominations, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1986
      - Administrative (Box 2)
      - Nominations, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - 1987
      - Administrative (Box 2)
      - Nominations, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - 1988
      - Administrative (Box 3)
      - Nominations, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - 1989
      - Administrative (Box 3)
      - Nominations, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - 1990
      - Administrative (Box 3)
      - Nominations, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - 1991
      - Administrative (Box 3)
      - Nominations, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - 1992
      - Administrative (Box 3)
      - Nominations, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1993
      - Administrative, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Nominations, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Nominations (Box 4)
    - 1994
      - Administrative (Box 4)
      - Nominations, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1995
      - Administrative (Box 4)
      - Nominations, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1996
      - Administrative (Box 4)
      - Nominations, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1997
      - Administrative (Box 4)
      - Nominations, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Sigma Xi Forum
    - Forum Videotapes, 2001, 2 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
    - Forum Audiotapes, 2001, 2 audiocassettes (Box 5)
    - Forum transcripts, 2001 (Box 5)